<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth a shorte monycyon, or counsayle of the cure &amp; gouernaunce of a housholde accordynge vnto policy / taken out of a pystle of a great learned man called Bernarde syluestre.</title>
            <author>Bernard Silvestris, fl. 1136.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1530</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09367</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1967.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3799</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33151000</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33151000</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28858</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09367)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28858)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1864:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth a shorte monycyon, or counsayle of the cure &amp; gouernaunce of a housholde accordynge vnto policy / taken out of a pystle of a great learned man called Bernarde syluestre.</title>
                  <author>Bernard Silvestris, fl. 1136.</author>
                  <author>Whitford, Richard, fl. 1495-1555?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Robert Wyer,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1530?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>STC (2nd ed.) attributes translation to R. Whitford.</note>
                  <note>Contains illustrated t.p., tail piece, init.</note>
                  <note>Colophon reads: Here endeth the boke Intytuled the gouernaunce of housholde. Imprynted by me Robert wyer, dwellyng at the sygne of seynt John Euangelist in seynt Martyns parysshe in the bysshop of Norwytche rentes, besyde Charinge crosse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: John Rylands University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Home economics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:1"/>
            <p>Here begynneth A ſhorte monycyon, or counſayle of the cure &amp; gouernaunce of a houſholde / accordynge vnto policy: taken out of a pyſtle of a great lerned man, cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Bernarde ſylueſtre.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>modified printer's device of Robert Wyer, with his name,the eagle, and part of the foreground cut away (McKerrow 67β)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere good &amp; deuoute Chryſtyans / fyrſte ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke moſt hede / and gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue moſt dylygence to ordre your ſelfe / and all youres, vnto oure lorde accordynge vnto the poore leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that comes after: and than ſe wel vnto the ſubſtaunce and gydynge of youre houſe / and goodes. Se fyrſte that peace be in the houſe / and that you agre all togyther, for els al your goodes wyll ſoone goo to noughte. Than (after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune prouerbe) cut your thonges: after or accordyng vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to your ledder. Spende accordynge vnto your gaynes: gettynges or ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and not aboue. It is alſo good polycye: to haue one yeres rent / or an yeres gaynes in ſtore for chaunces / whiche is not contrarye vnto chriſty anyte: where extreme or verey ſtreyte nede: is not perceyued in the neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure. A neglygent or retcheles per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone
<pb facs="tcp:28858:3"/> may ſoone ſet on fyne, &amp; deſtroy great ſubſtaunce. Haue therfore a good iye / and garde vnto the dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, for vnder them your goodes may ſoone mynyſſhe &amp; be waſted before you knowe / beware or haue knowleg therof. yf your goo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des begynne to waſte: better is / and leſſe rebuke for you to abſteyne / and withdrawe your charges: than to fal in to nedynes / or daunger. An olde prouerbe. Qui plus expendit <expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> copia tendit. Non admiretur ſi pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertate grauetur. That is.
<q>
                  <l>who ſo done ſpende beyonde theyr faculte.</l>
                  <l>No meruayle though with nede they greued be.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>¶It is therfore a great prouydence and good foreſyght often to counte / and compare your goodes / and your gaynes with your expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes. Often to ouerſe your good: ſhall be neceſſary. For your beeſtes may take hurte for
<pb facs="tcp:28858:4"/> defaute of fode (all thoughe they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge axe) ne complayne. The ſlepe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſbande: maketh a fatte dong hylle. And the iye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter, a faſt hors. That is to meane that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the mayſter: in euery corner: is moche profytable. Sumptuous &amp; coſtlye weddynges, or brydales, ben damage / without honoure. Expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces done vpon warre / ben more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable / than profytable. Better is to ſuffre ſome wronge, and to bye peace than to make warre / or to kepe war. Coſte made vpon ꝓdygal perſones / is clerely loſt. Coſt made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kyn or fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des / is reſonable. Fede your houſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holde ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes with honeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune fare / without delycates. For the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt that is made a gloton ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer after mende his maners. Gloto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is vyle fylthy / &amp; ſtynkynge &amp; wyll make the neglygent and careles per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon ſoone roten and ſhort lyfe. Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fedynge with ſcarcyte: is vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:28858:4"/> dilygent perſon pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. Vpon the holy dayes &amp; hyghe feſtes: gyue your houſholde plentye of mete: but ſelden &amp; fewe delycates. For the vſe of delycate fode / wyll ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne marre a good ſeruaunt. Let gloto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye and thy purſe ſtryue / and go to lawe togyther / and beware thou wel whiche parte thou takeſt / but for the moſte parte alway hold with the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe. For glotonous men of lawe &amp; the witneſſers: done ſpeke of all affeccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. but the purs bryngeth in playne euy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dence and profe / the empty barne &amp; the empty bag. But yf very nygardy ſhut vp thy purſe / than art not thou an eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge. For nygardy is a folyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhe &amp; nedeles fere / &amp; euer lyuynge in pouerte / and hurdeth &amp; muckerythe vp: he can not tell for whom. yf thou haue plenty of corne: deſyre no derth For thoſe perſones that of couetous mynde done procure or deſyre derthe done procure and deſyre the dethe of
<pb facs="tcp:28858:5"/> the pore / and ſhall be accuſed: as ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>micides and manſleers / ſell thy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne better chepe vnto thy neyghboure (al though he were thy enemy) than vnto ſtraungers, For an enemy is ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme ſoner vaynquyſſhed and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comen by a kynde dede / than by the ſwerde. Be neuer at debate with thy neyghboure / but rather ſtudye and laboure to be at one. For thou canſte haue none ſo ſure a caſtell / or garde of thy lyfe / as is loue and frendſhyp of thy neyghboure / yf thou ſuſpecte the women of thy houſe: let other per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones rather ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> / than thou ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be ouer buſy to try out the mater. For though it were of thy owne wyf, or the wyfe of thy huſbande: it were better vnknowen. For ones knowen it is neuer cured / the wounde is with out remedy. yf any remedy be / it ſhal be whan lyke chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is herd of other perſones. The leſte &amp; moſte eaſy way therin is to diſſimule y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater though
<pb facs="tcp:28858:5"/> it were pryuely knowen / &amp; pretende yngnoraunce without any quarel or countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / but rather by a dyſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ghoſtly father let the partyes be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fourmed that ſynne be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynued A noble herte / and hygh gentyl myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / wyll neuer ſerche of womens ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Aſhrewe wyll ſoner be correctid by ſmylynge or laughyng / than by a ſtaffe / or ſtrokes. The beſt way to ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe a woman good / is gentyll intrety and neuer to let her know that ſhe is ſuſpecte / and euer to be counceyled &amp; informed with louyng maner. an old woman vnclene of lyuynge (yf the lawe wolde ſuffre) ſhulde be buryed quycke. Let your clothynge or araye be in amene / nother vyle ne precious but alway fayre and honeſt / &amp; of ſad &amp; not of wanton faſſhyon. A coſtelye garment beyonde: or aboue the ſtate and degre of the perſon / is a ſygne &amp; token of lytell wytte. For a woman y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath ſuffycyent aray / to deſyre newe
<pb facs="tcp:28858:6"/> and chaunge / is a ſygne of lytell ſad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. Truſt hym rather for thy frende that ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what dothe for the / than hym that dothe offre hym ſelfe / ſaynge. I am yours in all I can and may. For in wordes is great plente of frendes a true frende loueth at all tymes and neuer fayleth at nede. There is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paryſon of ryches / vnto a faythefull frende. Neuer repute ne thynke hym thy frende / that dothe prayſe / or boſt the vnto thy face / or in thy preſence. whan you gyue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyle vnto a fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / ſay this ſemeth beſt vnto me / not thus you muſte nedely doo. For you may ſoner gette rebuke or blame for your counceyle yf it pryue not / than thanke, for youre goode counceyle: though it ſpede well / yf mynſtrelles / iogulers / or ieſters come to thy how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / ſay thou haſte no lodgynge for ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ieſters / you kepe nether ynne nor aleſtake. For yf you take pleaſure in theyr paſtymes you ben full lyke to
<pb facs="tcp:28858:6"/> haue another wyfe ſhortly after who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe name is called pouerte / or beggry. yf you fortune to come where they ben / and begyn ſomwhat to delecte in theyr maters: I aduyſe you dyſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mule &amp; take vpon you that you herd theym not / ne ſet any thynge therby. For yf they perceyue and ſe you but laugh: they wyll take that for an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to crye largeſſe &amp; to haue reward And ſo importune wyll they be / and ſo ſhamfully craue: that you ſhall be yrke and wery of them / and perauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture they wyll fall to rebukyng / brau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng / and ſcoldynge / ſo that you ſhal be fayne / and glade: to gyue ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>what for fere vnto thoſe galowe clapers / worthy in dede to be hanged vp. For I tell you / god is not pleaſed with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> occupacyon / excepte it be (as ſcant to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lerable or alowable) among prynces lordes / and hygh eſtates. Nowe for your ſeruauntes / yf you haue a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt of hygh proude mynde &amp; ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne
<pb facs="tcp:28858:7"/> ſtomacke put hym away leſte after he do you harme / &amp; ſoo do hym that alwaye dothe prayſe youre ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in all thynges. For a flaterer is worſe than an enemy / your enemye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not lyghtly deceyue you, but your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or your neyghboures that done prayſe you: ben ſurely about to deceyue you. Yf you haue a baſhful &amp; dredfull ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; fynde hym fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue hym &amp; cheryſſhe hym as your own natural child. Make your byldynges rather for nede, than for pleaſur. For the appetyte of byldyng for pleaſur ſhall neuer haue ende / tyl pouerte teche wyt ſome what to late. Be lothe to ſell your herytage, and if you muſt nede / ſell. Sell not to grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te perſones / but rather for leſſe vnto the lower perſones. Better is to ſell than to borow by vſery. For vſery is lyke a thefe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wold warne you before what harme he wolde do vnto you / Yf you bye or bargayne / be not botye
<pb facs="tcp:28858:7"/> felowe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great ꝑſones. And though he be vnder you / yet ſtryue not with hym leſte he put his parte vnto your better / or mayſter. In all thynges ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe truely and faythfully your bonde and promyſe / accordynge vnto your couenaunte. Due temporaunce is a thyng of great honeſtye in a houſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / let therfor your drynke wyne / ale or bere be temporate. Stronge dryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke is more pleaſaunt / than holſome. The wyſeman ſayth / that ſobre dryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke is the helth bothe of ſoule &amp; bodye And the wyſe &amp; lerned perſone, wyll be ryght well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with lytell dryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / and that ſhall not trouble the ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>macke, but rather cauſe ſwete &amp; hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſlepe / and of the contrary done come many incommodytes as there dothe folow. who ſo euer amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and dyuers ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge drynkes / with aboundaunce therof, is ſobre may be called an erthly god / or a god vpon erth / wraſtle not therwith yf you doo
<pb facs="tcp:28858:8"/> my counſell. And yf by chaunce you be in company / and begyn to fele the drynke worke / aryſe &amp; departe / a ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe is more meite for you, than any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany. who ſo by wordes wold excuſe dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes: dothe openly declare his owne dyſeaſe. The knowlege &amp; iuge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of wynes: doth nothyng become a yonge ꝑſone. Yf a phyſycyon or ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyon vſe to be dronke / lette hym not haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cure of your dyſeaſe / ne let no ne of them take experyence / and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in you: howe to cure / or hele ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For though they be well lerned and haue not experye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / it is no wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to let them proue theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng vpon you. Great gay horſe / &amp; lytel prety dogges: leue you vnto lordes &amp; ladyes. A bygge labourynge hors / and a maſtyfe / or a curre dogge: ben good to kepe your houſe. As for hau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes / houndes / and huntyng dogges do ſpende more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do get, they ben mete &amp; accordynge for ſtates: to
<pb facs="tcp:28858:8"/> ſet ydle ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes on werke but ferre vnaccordynge ben they: for buſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and ware houſholders. It is no wyſdom to make your owne chylder ſtewardes or rulers of your houſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de or goodes. Foles and neglygente or careles perſones: haue many myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes. For that is theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune excuſe whan any thynge is wronge, they ſay than / that chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or myſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune was cauſe therof. I ſay not nay but that chaunce or myſfortune may fall. But who ſo doth folowe wyſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lernynge / &amp; dyſcrecyon, ſhall ſeldom accuſe myſfortune. For delyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>renes / and good hede, done ſeldome company with myſfortune. But yet more ſeldom ſhall you ſe myſfortune and ſlouthe or neglygence, departyd in ſondre, for they done co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany to gyther. The ſluggard ſayth god wyll helpe hym / and ſo longe he truſteth ther vnto, tyll he be brought vnto beggery. For god by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:28858:9"/> doth ſende the ſluggarde (for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple) vnto the ant or piſmere, to lerne to la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour. For man ſayth Iob is borne to laboure / as a byrde to flye. Kepe you therfore but few ydle perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or men. And watche you and take good hede vnto euery perſone of youre houſe / &amp; euer ponder / wey / and conſydre your exſpences / with your gaynes / or get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges. Fyrſt get and brynge in / and than ſpende. For it is no good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry to borowe. And when ye wex aged / truſt rather vnto god / than vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to your chylder / or frendes / that you ſende before you / you ſhall be ſure to fynde. No cofre / chyſt / ne tower may be more ſure to kepe treaſure than is heuen. Let not therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore paſſe you. what you gyue to them, you gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vnto Cryſte. And of that you leue behynde you, appoynt it vnto euery perſone his part. For better were for you nothynge to leue / than that ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe and debate ſhulde be made / conſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:28858:9"/> blemyſſhed / and god offendyd / for your goodes. Truſt them beſte to do for your ſoule / not that done loue or ſay they done loue your ſoule / but that you done perceyue and coniectu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, done loue theyr owne ſoule. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke your teſtament euery yere newe / &amp; ſurely ſealyd by wytnes. Lay it whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re (whan nede is) it maye be founde / no man is ſure how to ende his lyfe. The moſte ſure waye, to dye well / is well to lyue / whiche he graunte vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bought vs our lord god &amp; moſt ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſauyoure Iheſu chryſte. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>¶Here endeth the boke Intytuled the gou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
               <desc>•</desc>
            </gap>rnaunce of houſholde.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprynted by me Robert wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, dwellyng at the ſygne of ſeynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſt / in ſeynt Martyns pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe in the byſſhop of Norwytche ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, beſyde Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge croſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:10"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>ROBERT <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
                     </gap> WYER.</head>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Wyer, including his name and mark,with St. John the Evangelist and the eagle</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:11"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28858:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
